[SPEAKER_00]: Ajahn, I'm wondering when I should punish the mind versus simply not just giving in to what it's demanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because sometimes it's obvious it's telling you do this and there's a lot of pressure and you simply just don't do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But other times it seems like there would be more room for
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's less of a demand that it's making and it's more just acting out and you want to send it a message still.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, a practical example that I could give of that is that I think anybody staying at a monastery will relate to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Say you're expecting a day to not have any work and something comes up and you find yourself like you're not very happy with that.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you... an example of then punishing the mind in that case, if it's really acting out and resisting that, would be to say, well, okay, I see that you're kicking and screaming now.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, next time we actually have a day off, we're working anyways, just to send it that message.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, is that... is that kind of an acceptable way of punishing the mind?
[SPEAKER_00]: And how do you know when to do that versus when to be a bit more passive?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I would say so, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I would say that's... because the choice and the decision has to be, as I say, referenced by, informed by, the state of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because people can easily just fall into blind determination.
[SPEAKER_01]: So they... the mind got upset because you had to work, and then, well, from now on, forever, I will always work.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I won't have to deal with this problem again, in other words.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a mistake.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like falling into that kind of overly determined dhūtaṅga kind of level of practice, because it just blinds you to the reference point.
[SPEAKER_01]: It covers it up again.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if it's like... Oh, yeah, so the mind's kicking and screaming.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not acting out of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm doing the work anyway.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, the mind's kicking and screaming again, on another occasion.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, well, how about we, as in me and my mind, we decide we'll work now, even on the quiet days.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you stop kicking and screaming.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like made, the determination is made to the right extent, addressed at the right thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you still keep it on your mind, you know, just like, oh, now I will just power through and work and never think about anything again.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind's still alive, very much so, and it's going to complain.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's like... that is the level to sustain the determination.
[SPEAKER_01]: And those type of determinations made on that right level, that are directly speaking to the mind, not just coming out of some overly zealous, eh... let me just crack down onto this, eh... they're the ones that are the most efficient.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if on that level, you decide to never give in to a central thought again, as a determination, you are going directly to anāgāmī, at least.
[SPEAKER_01]: If on that level, you decide and sustain, I will never have thoughts of ill-will.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, like, mind might come up with them, but I will never take that up.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, the whole space between you and the mind, it's even more than outlined, cleared,
[SPEAKER_01]: Highlighted, and then you have, like, like, what's left is the mind with its own thoughts, which then mind gets to see, like, oh, because there's no more interference from you through your choices and falling into traps and accepting and acting out everything that blurs the lines, blurs the picture.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, so that's the the ignorance that the Buddha refers to.
[SPEAKER_01]: The ignorance that obscures pretty much you and your own mind and stuff in between and and what contributes to what.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it kind of reminds me of, when we talk about not having abstract contemplations, keeping things concrete, it seems like if your, quote, dūtanga practices are also concrete, and in reference to... Well, exactly, in the reference to the exact, exact level,
[SPEAKER_01]: And think about it, like now, like the example you gave.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, say, you decided, because the mind's been coming up with stuff repeatedly, it's like, okay, now we'll work on the quietness.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I decided that for you, as in, for the animal inside.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't need to be overly dramatic or just... we're doing this now.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then the mind says, oh, let's not do it, let's do this.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, we're sticking to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm the one who decides what we stick to, basically, because the mind can't act on its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, imagine now exactly the same thing, exactly the same principle applied to accepting the central thoughts when the mind presents you with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Accepting the thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not, like, not having them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're not, like, they don't originate from you.
[SPEAKER_01]: They come up.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why even arahants in the suttas and anāgāmī says they purify thoughts in their arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're not the ones doing the arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the same principle you decide when the mind, whenever you come up with these thoughts in this internal space, with the thoughts of, as the Sutta says, the thoughts of sensuality, thoughts of cruelty, thoughts of ill-will, I won't pick them up.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's our determination here.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you know, you go, you walk, you talk, you go to toilet, you eat, you sleep.
[SPEAKER_01]: That doesn't change.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's that, like, happily practicing in the suttas above sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, and you could see how people would, like, again, you read about it, you sort of wrap your head around it, and then, but you can't possibly, just on the basis of mere information alone,
[SPEAKER_01]: Make that determination, they would stay on that right level.
[SPEAKER_01]: They wouldn't become too much or too little.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, you can't possibly get the right tune from the... of the music simply by reading the paper.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to keep playing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Tuning the strings, playing it, tuning the strings, tighter, looser, tighter, looser, until your ear gets to discern the sound in between, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the more you're familiar with it, then you're not even fiddling with the strings anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: You go straight into the tune.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the right level that I keep talking about, which can be revealed only, like, as I said, if you endure the pressure to act out.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you don't act out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Coarsely, it's gonna take... depends on how, you know, corrupted the minds were.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's gonna take some time, but eventually, as I said, those those mental choices will become more obvious, will become clearer.
[SPEAKER_01]: It wouldn't be something just abstract.
[SPEAKER_01]: You would be, like, recognizing your direct involvement in maintenance of, like, say, a choice of accepting sensual thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: When they come up, you... it's like, oh, I have taken this up.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not acting out, I'm not saying anything, I'm not doing anything, not breaking the precepts, but mentally I have accepted it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I have taken it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I feel like, oh...
[SPEAKER_01]: So how about I don't take that very mental layer?
[SPEAKER_01]: And that decision can become apparent and made rightly, that choice, that cetanā of the right kind, only if you would have actually purified your behavior by body and speech up to that level.
[SPEAKER_01]: Otherwise, you can hear about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It can make perfect sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: But when you do it, it's going to be completely out of tune.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not going to be pertaining to the right note.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, again, you're doing it on account of non-purified physical behavior and actions and so on.